<article xmlns:c="http://www.C.org"
         xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org">

<title>Implementing the RGraphicsDevice package</title>

<section>
<title>Motivation</title>
<para>
The idea is to try to automate much of this as there is very little
going on. Essentially, for a graphics device, we need to provide C
routines that implement each of the function pointer fields.  Each
must accept its arguments, convert them to R objects, call the
corresponding R function, converting the result to the corresponding C
type and returning that to the R graphics engine.  This is a job for
the RGCCTranslationUnit package.  In addition to implementing these
simple C routines, we also want to provide R programmers with access
to the fields of the data structures.
</para>
</section>

<section r:eval="false">
<title>Exploring the data structures</title>
<para>
We first start by generating a translation unit description for the
R graphics device structure. 
We do this by creating a C file that includes Rinternals, R_ext/GraphicsEngine.h and
R_ext/GraphicsDevice. Then we create the TU file from that by compiling
that file with gcc and the flag -fdump-translation-unit.
This is done in the TU directory of this package.
</para>
<para>
Given the TU file, let's read it into R and look at the data structures.
<r:code>
library(RGCCTranslationUnit)
tu = parseTU("TU/gd.c.t00.tu")
ds = getDataStructures(tu) 
</r:code>
We know which structure(s) we want, namely the <c:type>DevDesc</c:type>.
The following returns a <r:class>ResolvedTypeReference</r:class>
so we resolve it again to get the <r:class>StructDefinition</r:class>:
<r:code>
DevDesc = resolveType(ds$DevDesc, tu)
DevDesc = resolveType(DevDesc, tu)
</r:code>
This contains a description of the fields, amongst other details.
</para>
<para>
Now, let's look at the function pointers which are like "methods"
for an instance of a device.
<r:code>
i = sapply(DevDesc@fields, function(x) class(x@type)) == "FunctionPointer"
funs = DevDesc@fields[i]

 # ensure that the parameters, etc. are fully resolved
funs = lapply(funs, function(x) {
                      x@type = resolveType(x@type, tu)
                      x
                    })
</r:code>
The <r:func>lapply</r:func> call ensures that the parameters are all fully resolved.
</para>
<para>
Let's look at the types of the parameters in these function pointers:
<r:code>
table(sapply(unlist(sapply(funs, function(x) 
                                   lapply(x@type@parameters, slot, "type")), 
                    recursive = FALSE), 
      class))
<r:output><![CDATA[
          CString        doubleType           intType       PointerType
                5                23                 4                13
TypedefDefinition
               32
]]></r:output>
</r:code>
So we see the basic types (integers, doubles, character strings)
and a typedef and pointers.
We'll dig down further into these generic pointers and typedefs:
<r:code>
params = unlist(sapply(funs, function(x) lapply(x@type@parameters, slot, "type")), recursive = FALSE)
f = function(x)  {
           if(is(x, "PendingType") || is(x, "ResolvedTypeReference"))
              x = resolveType(x, tu)
           if(is(x, "PointerType") || is(x, "TypedefDefinition")) 
              f(x@type)
           else 
              x
         }
tp = sapply(params, f)
table(sapply(tp, function(x) 
                    if(is(x, "StructDefinition")) 
                      x@name 
                    else if(is(x, "PendingType")) 
                      x@name 
                    else class(x)))
<r:output><![CDATA[
     charType    doubleType       intType      pDevDesc R_GE_gcontext
            5            36             4            20            11
      SEXPREC
            1
]]></r:output>
</r:code>
So we see a pointer to a DevDesc, R_GE_gcontext and the regular 
R object type in C (SEXP or SEXPREC).
</para>
<para>
Let's also look at the non-function pointer fields:
<r:code>
names(DevDesc@fields[!i])
<r:output><![CDATA[
 [5] "clipLeft"                "clipRight"
 [7] "clipBottom"              "clipTop"
 [9] "xCharOffset"             "yCharOffset"
[11] "yLineBias"               "ipr"
[13] "cra"                     "gamma"
[15] "canClip"                 "canChangeGamma"
[17] "canHAdj"                 "startps"
[19] "startcol"                "startfill"
[21] "startlty"                "startfont"
[23] "startgamma"              "deviceSpecific"
[25] "displayListOn"           "canGenMouseDown"
[27] "canGenMouseMove"         "canGenMouseUp"
[29] "canGenKeybd"             "gettingEvent"
[31] "hasTextUTF8"             "wantSymbolUTF8"
[33] "useRotatedTextInContour" "reserved"
]]></r:output>
table(sapply(DevDesc@fields[!i], function(x)  class(x@type)))
<r:output><![CDATA[
ArrayType            doubleType EnumerationDefinition
         3                    14                    11
   intType           PointerType
         5                     1
]]></r:output>
</r:code>
These maintain the state of the graphics device.
We will want access to these values, to both query and set them.
</para>
</section>

<section r:eval="false">
<title>The Desired Code</title>
<para>
Ideally, we would simply call generateStructInterface.
This will handle generating much of the interface, but
there are different considerations we want to explore.
Firstly, for each of our function pointers,
we will have a C routine that provides a proxy.
Each of these will find the corresponding R function
for the device. If this is <r:null/>, the C routine
does nothing. If there is an R function, it invokes that.
</para>
<para>
How do we find the corresponding R function for a C routine?  We can
either have a list of R functions or, alternatively, a C-level
structure with a SEXP for each individual function.  The benefit of
having a separate structure is slightly more direct access relative to
calling <c:code>VECTOR_ELT(funs, i)</c:code> and having to use numbers/enums to index
into that list, e.g. CIRCLE.
So we would define a structure such as
<c:code>
typedef struct {
  SEXP text;
  SEXP strWidth;
  SEXP size;
    ..
} RDevDescMethods; 
</c:code>
We could even use an array of SEXP objects rather than a struct
as the offsets are fixed.
</para>
<para>

We would then create an instance of this and store it in the
<c:field>deviceSpecific</c:field> field of the 
<c:type>pDevDesc</c:type> object.
We will populate it with R functions. 
We have an R function that has a parameter for each of the methods
and creates an instance of this <c:type>RDevDescMethods</c:type>
structure and fills in each value that is provided by the caller.
We should test the number of parameters
each function accepts to ensure they are compatible.
</para>

<para>
So the top-level R function to create an R-level graphics device
would look something like
<r:code>
createGraphicsDevice =
function(text = NULL, line = NULL, circle = NULL, ...)
{
  devMethods = .Call("R_create_RDevDesc", text, line, circle, ....)
  dev = .Call("R_create_DevDesc")
  dev$deviceSpecific = .Call("R_createGraphicsDevice", devMethods)
  dev$canClip = FALSE
  dev$canHAdj = TRUE
    ...

  dev
}
</r:code>
There may be an issue with registering the device before its fields
are initialized, so we may need to separate creation and registration in R_createGraphicsDevice.
</para>
<para>
The C routines that we set for the DevDesc function pointers will be something along the lines
<c:code id="R_circle">
void 
R_circle(double x, double y, double r, const pGEcontext gc, pDevDesc dd)
{
  RDevDescMethods *methods = (RDevDescMethods *) dd->deviceSpecific;
  SEXP e, cur;

  if(!methods->circle || methods->circle == R_NilValue) 
    return;

  PROTECT(cur = e = allocVector(LANGSXP, 6));
  SETCAR(cur, methods->circle); cur = CDR(cur);
  SETCAR(cur, ScalarReal(x)); cur = CDR(cur);
  SETCAR(cur, ScalarReal(y)); cur = CDR(cur);
  SETCAR(cur, ScalarReal(r)); cur = CDR(cur);
  SETCAR(cur, mkRef(gc, "GEcontext")); cur = CDR(cur);
  SETCAR(cur, mkRef(dd, "DevDesc")); 

  Rf_eval(e, R_GlobalEnv);
}
</c:code>
Note that we could create each of these calls 
just once and store those in the RDevDescMethod structure.
This is just a minor modification to how we generate the code and would make the code more efficient.
</para>
<para>
So we need a class definition for a reference to a DevDesc and also
for a reference to a GEcontext.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Generating the Code</title>
<para>
The first thing we can do is to create code for
the <c:type>RDevDescMethods</c:type> type that we introduced
earlier. This does not exist in the C code for the graphics device
and is a construct for  our interface.
We can write the definition and the accessor code for the
fields. However, it is more convenient to programmatically
generate this by "pretending" it was in the C code definitions 
we read. We can programmatically construct a description
of such a C-level structure.
This is a structure with a SEXP for each of the function pointers
in the <c:type>DevDesc</c:type> structure.
So one thing we can do is to copy the <r:var>funs</r:var> 
list describing the function pointers and change 
the type of each to be a SEXP.
<r:code>
sexp = resolveType(ds$SEXP, tu)
fields = lapply(funs, function(x) {
                           x@type = sexp
                           x
                        })
</r:code>
Then we can create a StructDefinition object with
these fields and put that within a TypedefDefinition
to be able to refer to this via the name 
<c:type>RDevDescMethods</c:type>:
<r:code>
devDescMethods = new("TypedefDefinition", 
                     name = "RDevDescMethods",
                     type = new("StructDefinition", 
                                name = "RDevDescMethods",
                                fields = fields))
</r:code>
We can now use all the  code generation facilities
in RGCCTranslationUnit to create an interface to this
data type.
</para>

<para>
The next task is to create the C routines that will act as proxies
and pass the C-level arguments to the corresponding R functions
(see <xref linkend="R_circle"/>).
We'll do this for just one (circle) and look at the result.
We call <r:func>createProxyRCall</r:func> and give it the
FunctionPointer that will be called. We also give it the name of 
the C routine to define. And the third argument is 
code C code to access the R function corresponding to this function.
<r:code>
createProxyRCall(funs[["circle"]]@type, "R_circle", 
                   "((RDevDescMethods*) (r5->deviceSpecific))->circle")
</r:code>
So we do this for all of the function pointers with a "simple" loop.
Unfortunately, the function pointer getEvent does not have a 
parameter providing a DevDesc reference. This means we cannot readily
access the device specific data and hence the corresponding R 
function. So for the moment, we'll just exclude that.
<r:code>
funs = funs[ - match("getEvent", names(funs)) ]
</r:code>
Now we can generate the code for all the function pointers.
<r:code>
proxyNames = structure(paste("R", names(funs), sep = "_"), 
                       names = names(funs))
code = mapply(createProxyRCall,
              lapply(funs, slot, "type"),
              proxyNames,
              paste("((RDevDescMethods*) ( r", 
                    sapply(funs, function(x) length(x@type@parameters)), 
                    "->deviceSpecific))->", names(funs), sep = ""))

</r:code>
<ignore>
# Good to add but need to determine if void type or not and return or return(ans)
#   paste("if(r", sapply(funs, function(x) length(x@type@parameters)), " == NULL || r",
#   sapply(funs, function(x) length(x@type@parameters)), "->deviceSpecific == NULL) return(ans);", sep = ""))
</ignore>
Note that we have to know how many parameters there are for each routine to be able
to correctly create the C code to access the <c:type>pDevDesc</c:type> parameter.
It would be simpler if the compiler emitted the parameter names for a routine and we could refer to this
as <c:var>dd</c:var> as it is in the header files.
Unfortunately, this only happens for routine definitions, not declarations.
</para>

<para>
The next thing to create is the code that initializes the DevDesc
with these routines. We have the names in <r:var>proxyNames</r:var>, 
so we can generate this code easily as (assuming a variable named
<c:var>dd</c:var> representing the <c:type>pDevDesc</c:type>)
<r:code>
init = c("dd->deviceSpecific = calloc(1, sizeof(RDevDescMethods));",
         "if(!dd->deviceSpecific) return(0);",
         paste("dd ->", names(proxyNames), "=", proxyNames, ";"),
         "return(1);")
</r:code>
We can put this in code we write or specify it as the body of a new C routine
which we can call:
<r:code>
init = CRoutineDefinition("initializeDevDescMethods", 
                          c("int", "initializeDevDescMethods(pDevDesc dd)", "{", init, "}"))
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
We'll manually write the code to create the graphics device and call this initialization
routine as this is specialized code that depends on knowing R internals.
See <c:routine>R_createGraphicsDevice</c:routine> in Rgd.c.
</para>
<para>
(Need writeCode method for devDescMethods. Done now?)
<r:code><![CDATA[
con = file("src/proxy.c", "w")
writeIncludes(c("<Rdefines.h>", "<R_ext/GraphicsEngine.h>", "<R_ext/GraphicsDevice.h>"), con)

writeCode(devDescMethods@type, "C", con)
writeCode(devDescMethods, "C", con)

idevDescMethods = generateStructInterface(devDescMethods, DefinitionContainer(tu))
writeCode(idevDescMethods, "C", con)
writeCode(idevDescMethods, "R", "R/devDescMethods.R")

cat(paste(sapply(code, as, "character"), collapse = "\n\n"), file = con)
writeCode(init, "C", file = con)
close(con)
]]></r:code>
</para>
<para>
Next we need an R function and C routine that sets the fields of the
<c:type>RDevDescMethods</c:type>.  This is used to initialize the
fields of the RDevDescMethods in the <c:field>deviceSpecific</c:field>
field of the <c:type>DevDesc</c:type> structure.  We can have a single
function that accepts values for all the fields and sets them in a
single operation, or we can have individual routines to set each
field. It is easy to create the latter using
<r:func>generateStructInterface</r:func> (at least it is intended to
be!) and this generates the corresponding class definition.  C routine
to instantiate a C version, provide methods for getting and setting
individual elements via the $ operatoretc, ...  We do this with the
<r:func>generateStructInterface</r:func> call in the code above.

</para>
<para>
After this, we need to be able to access and set the fields in the
DevDesc. This is a run-time facility so that the R programmer
can query and modify a particular graphics device.
(See TU/tu.R for details.)
<r:code>
devDesc.sub = DevDesc
devDesc.sub@fields = devDesc.sub@fields[!i] 
idevDesc = generateStructInterface(devDesc.sub, DefinitionContainer(tu))
</r:code>
</para>
</section>

</article>
